Guide to the Andrews Memorial Bookplate Collection of Irene D. Andrews Pace (Early American Bookplates)
Yale University Arts Library
Andrews Memorial Bookplate Collection of Irene D. Andrews Pace (Early American Bookplates)
1640-1920
BKP 6
Yale University Arts Library
0.83
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of early American bookplates commissioned by both individuals and institutions, as well as correspondence and ephemeral materials related to the collection.
Andrews, Irene Dwen, 1892-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Irene D. Andrews Pace, 1963, in memory of Dr. Edmund Andrews (Yale 1913) and his father, Dr. E. Wyllys Andrews.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Born Irene Greene Dwen, Mrs. Pace (1892-1962) was an avid bookplate collector from the early 1920s until 1962. In addition to over 150,000 plates in her collection, she also maintained a reference library related to bookplates, as well as heraldry and biographical research. Pace commissioned several hundred bookplates for herself. In 1936, she published Owners of Books: The Dissipations of a Collector.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of early American bookplates commissioned by both individuals and institutions, as well as correspondence and ephemera related to the collection.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates - Individuals. II. Bookplates - Organizations, Institutions, and Businesses. III. Bookplates - Unidentified. IV. Correspondence and Ephemera. Within each series, bookplates are arranged alphabetically. Any correspondence or ephemeral materials relating to a specific bookplate are filed together with the bookplate.
Bookplates, American; Bookplates
- Bookplates – Individuals, Series I
  Arrangement
  A collection of private bookplates arranged alphabetically by the patron's surname.
  - Abercrombie – Agnew, 1783-1905 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander – Andrews, 1830 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anstruther – Atkinson, 1712-1850; 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Atwood – I. Bancker, 1770-1820 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bancroft – Bayard, 1860-1890 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beck – Betton, 1860 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bigelow – Boucher, 1753-1879 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bouchier – Brent, 1794-1917 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brewster – Bushnell, 1816-1839 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Byrd – Campart, 1725-1901 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cambell of Monzie – Carmichaell, 1730-1900 undated; 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charles Carroll – James Carroll, 1790-1894 undated; 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cary – Chauncy, 1768-1784 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chester – Clowes, 1780-1834 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Collet – Craven, 1675-1838 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Croft – Davidson, 1845 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Davis – Dillingham, 1736 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dinwiddie – Duane, 1760-1770 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Duer – Edmeston, undated; 5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - B. Edwards – W.H. Edwards, 1760-1850 undated; 8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Elam – Everett, 1780-1876 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ewing – Fish, 1880 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fitch – Friend, 1803 undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Gardiner – Giles, 1875 undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gilpin – Gray, 1848 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Green – Griswold, 1757-1859; undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gutheri – Harper, 1760 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Harrison – Hill, 1780 undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - E.A. Hitchcock, 1798-1870 undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hobart – Hoyts, 1819-1850 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hubbard – Inglis, 1770-1819 undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ingraham – Jamaica, 1788-1845 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - James – Johnson, 1778-1860 undated; 8 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - John Johnston, 1780 undated; 5 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Jones – Lee, 1770-1809 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Lemperly – Livingston, undated; 11 items (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Livius – Lothrop, 1757-1837 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Lowell, James – Lowell, Robert, 1836 undated; 6 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Lyon – Markham, 1873 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Marryat – Mathias, 1836-1852 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Maude – Meflin, 1745-1873 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Meginness – Montgomery, 1750 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Moore – Morris, 1747-1780 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Morse – Newton, 1750 undated; 11 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Norris – Paine, 1748-1825 undated; 9 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Palmer – Parkman, 1808 undated; 8 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Parsons, H.M. – Penington, 1782-1860 undated; 8 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Penn, Richard – Penn William, 1703-1863 undated; 5 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Pennington – Turner, 1720-1885 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Tyler – Vassall, 1801 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Vaughan – Walcott, 1770-1790 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Wall - Watson, 1640-1860 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Webster – White, 1760-1852 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Whiting – Williamson, 1820-1895 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Willis – Zahm, 1747-1773 undated; 12 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Bookplates – Organizations, Institutions, and Businesses, Series II
  A collection of various library, university, social organization, and business bookplates arranged alphabetically.
  - American Antiquarian Society – Charlestown Library, 1630-1804 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Chelmsford, Social Library of – Erasmus Hall Library, 1811-1896 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Farmington Monthly Library – Hartford Young Men's Institute, 1822-1838 undated; 6 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Harvard College, 1750-1843 undated; 9 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    General note
    See also Folder 60.
  - Harvard College, 1750-1873 undated; 8 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    See also Folder 59.
  - Hasty Pudding Library – Newport, First Social Library in, 1794-1884 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Newburyport Public Library – New York Social Library, 1758-1865 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Northampton, General Library – Schuylkill College, 1704-1865 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Sears Library – U.S. Naval Observatory, 1804-1835 undated; 13 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Union Library – Yale University, 1810-1874 undated; 13 (Box 2, Folder 65)
- Bookplates – Unidentified, Series III
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains bookplates that have no patron or artist information.
  - Unidentified bookplates, undated; 4 (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Correspondence and Ephemera, Series IV
  This series contains letters of correspondence and other materials without attached bookplates.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically according to recipient.
  - Andrews – Pace, 1939-1953 undated; 4 (Box 2, Folder 67)